A Guide to the Edwards family letters, 1860-1865
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Edwards family letters, 1860-1865
The Library of Virginia
53808
.175 cubic feet (1 box)
Edwards family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Thomas L. Ackiss of Virginia Beach.
Biographical Information
Alexander Washington Edwards was born about 1835 in Princess Anne County, Virginia. He enlisted in Company C, 15th Virginia Cavalry, 27 March 1862 and was elected 2nd lieutenant. Edwards was captured by Union troops during the battle of Fredericksburg and was paroled. He returned to his company and was promoted to 1st lieutenant on 5 January 1863 and eventually commanded his company. Edwards was captured 11 May 1864 at the battle of Yellow Tavern and was sent to the prison camp at Point Lookout, Maryland. By July 1864 he was transferred to Fort Delaware, and became part of the group of Confederate officers known as the "Immortal 600" that was sent to South Carolina and Georgia and placed in line of Confederate fire in retaliation for Union officers put in a position of receiving friendly fire. In March 1865, those prisoners were returned to Fort Delaware. Edwards died 11 March 1865 en route to Fort Delaware. On 26 March 1857 he married Ann Virginia Brock. Ann Virginia Brock Edwards was born 7 January 1834 in Princess Anne County. The couple had no children. By 1886, Ann Virginia Brock Edwards had moved to Norfolk, Virginia. She applied for a widow's pension in 1903. Ann Virginia Edwards died 1 March 1904 and was buried in Elmwood Cemetery in Norfolk.
Scope and Content
Letters, 1860-1865, from Lieutenant A. W. Edwards (ca. 1835-1865) of Company C, 15th Virginia Cavalry, to his wife Ann Virginia Edwards (1834-1904), detailing his military activities during the war, providing news of friends in the company, and hoping for a Confederate victory in the war. Also includes correspondence between husband and wife after Edwards' capture at the battle of Spotsylvania, as well as correspondence regarding Edwards' death. Papers also include a promissory note, March 1860, and a recipe for a "cure to an eating cancer."
Contents List
- Papers, 1860 (Folder 1)
- Letters, March-July 1862 (Folder 2)
- Letters, October-November 1862 (Folder 3)
- Letters, 1863 (Folder 4)
- Letters, March-June 1864 (Folder 5)
- Letters, July 1864 (Folder 6)
- Letters, August 1864 (Folder 7)
- Letters, September-December 1864 (Folder 8)
- Letters, 1865 (Folder 9)
- Papers--cure to an eating cancer, undated (Folder 10)
- Transcriptions (Folder 11)